Guide to the Herman Axelbank Motion Picture Film Collection 1896-1977
Hoover Institution Archives
Herman Axelbank motion picture film collection,
1896-1977
79073
Axelbank, Herman, 1900-1979
271 motion picture film reels, 1 oversize box. (27 linear feet)
Hoover Institution Archives Stanford, California 94305-6010
Depicts major events in the twentieth-century Russian history, including the Russian Revolution and World Wars I and II, the tsarist family and court, communist political and military leaders, and scenes of economic, social, and cultural activities in the Soviet Union.
Administrative Information
Access
Closed in part. Reels 1-30, 32-36, 40-42, 47, 62, 90, 93, 97, 99, and 118-123 are open for research. All others are eligible to be opened after copies are made.
The Hoover Institution Archives only allows access to copies of audiovisual items. To listen to sound recordings or to view videos or films during your visit, please contact the Archives at least two working days before your arrival. We will then advise you of the accessibility of the material you wish to see or hear. Please note that not all audiovisual material is immediately accessible.
Acknowledgments
The Hoover Institution acquired the Herman Axelbank motion picture film collection in 1979 from the family of the late Herman Axelbank. Shortly thereafter, Mr. Alexander Kulakoff, who is a general partner of the Harrington-Kulakoff Development Company, Palo Alto, California, donated funds to describe, index, and produce preservation and use copies of the first 28 reels of the collection. Without his financial assistance, the Herman Axelbank collection could not now be made available for research by the scholarly community. I am pleased to acknowledge his generous support and interest.
Milorad M. Drachkovitch
Director of Archives and Senior Fellow
January 1983
Access Points
World War, 1914-1918.; World War, 1914-1918--Pictorial works.; World War, 1914-1918--Russia.; World War, 1939-1945.; World War, 1939-1945--Pictorial works.; World War, 1939-1945--Soviet Union.; Russia.; Soviet Union.; Soviet Union--History--Pictorial works.; Soviet Union--History--Revolution, 1917-1921--Pictorial works.; Soviet Union--Pictorial works.; Moving-pictures.; Video tapes.
Background
Herman Axelbank (1900-1979) devoted his energies for over fifty years to compiling a motion picture film chronicle of the last years of Imperial Russia, the Russian revolutions, and the new government which emerged from the upheaval. He was born in the village of Novo-Konstantinov, in the Russian Empire, on May 30, 1900; his family moved to New York in 1909. Fascinated with film-making from childhood, Axelbank got a job, in 1916, as an office boy for Samuel Goldfish (later Goldwyn) at Goldwyn Pictures on Forty-second Street. The news of the February Revolution in Russia captured the young Axelbank's imagination. "Wish I could take moving pictures over there; we don't have any of our own [American Revolution] in 1775," he remembered remarking to a co-worker.
At about that time Axelbank met a cameraman whose assignments took him to Eastern Europe. Axelbank commissioned him to film Lenin and Trotsky, pawning his possessions and borrowing from friends in order to pay the cameraman's advance. In 1922 the cameraman returned with film of such events as the Kronstadt Mutiny of March 1921 and the Trial of the Socialist Revolutionaries of 1922. With such a beginning, Axelbank's film archive was already noteworthy; in the 1920's the Pathe, International, and Fox news services, and even the Soviet government, purchased film from him.
Axelbank soon acquired film taken on the German, Austrian, and Turkish fronts during World War I, film of the Tsar and his family, and of scenes from pre-revolutionary Russia, including provincial towns as well as Moscow and St. Petersburg. In most instances the names of the cameramen and other circumstances surrounding the filming have not been preserved. Surviving bills of sale from the 1920's show that Jawitz Pictures Corporation sold Axelbank film footage of the Provisional Government (cameramen: Darovsky, Himmel, Rizhok, Borisof, Slonim, and Dzhakel), Petrograd and Moscow during the Russian Revolution (cameraman: Thompson), and the Lenin funeral; Noxall Film Company sold him footage on Tsarist Russia, Denikin, and Kolchak (cameramen: Risemann, Kubelik, and Hoffman); and Robitschek, Ehrlich and Company sold him footage of the city of Moscow. Other records were destroyed in a 1959 fire at the facility where Axelbank stored his flammable nitrate film. Many other acquisitions of the 1930's through the 1950's were accomplished by means of verbal agreements.
In 1918 Axelbank attended a lecture by John Reed and later did some filming for the Friends of Soviet Russia, but he never became deeply involved in politics. His primary interest remained his historical film project.
In 1921 Axelbank assisted the Friends of Soviet Russia in making the film "Russia Through the Shadows," which was shown to raise funds for Soviet famine relief. In 1922 he made the three-reel documentary "With the Movie Camera Through the Bolshevik Revolution" using the footage he had already collected. Meanwhile, he continued collecting more film from cameramen and emigres, sometimes making trips to Europe and concluding the deals at some risk to himself. In 1924 he made "The Truth About Russia." He regarded these feature films as the means to raise money for his collecting efforts and as the groundwork for his film "Tsar to Lenin."
In December 1928 Axelbank contacted Max Eastman, who had published "Lenin's Testament" in the West, and asked for his assistance in the editing and narration of "Tsar to Lenin." The project took about one year. (One of the narrators whose voice appears in the early reels of the Herman Axelbank Film Collection is Eastman.) During this period Eastman went to Prinkipo Island to film Trotsky and his family in exile there. "Tsar to Lenin" premiered at the Filmarte Theater in New York on March 6, 1937. Its presentation of the role of Trotsky and the Old Bolsheviks in the Revolution aroused the ire of American Communists loyal to Stalin's line. They picketed the theaters in which the film was shown.
Through the years Axelbank attributed events such as his being followed, thefts of film, and the 1959 fire in the facility where his film was stored to continuing Soviet displeasure with his film collecting efforts. Ironically, in the 1960's and early 1970's representatives of the Soviet Academy of Sciences and the Institute of Marxism-Leninism showed interest in buying the early reels of Axelbank's film collection. In all probability they were interested in filling in gaps in their own film records of Trotsky and other revolutionaries whom Stalin had eliminated from the Soviet film archives as well as from life.
Scope of the Collection
The Herman Axelbank Film Collection consists of 266 reels containing over 250,000 feet of film, primarily newsreel and documentary footage. The editing of the film and its chronological arrangement are the work of Axelbank. As attested by the desire of the Soviet representatives to purchase the first forty-four reels of the collection, the footage on these reels, taken during the period from about 1901 to 1937, is extremely rare; some portions are unique. Included are the Tsar, his family, and associates in moments of relaxation as well as at official ceremonies; the Russian revolutions of 1917; the Civil War, with especially good coverage of Siberia and the Far East; and revolutionary and governmental leaders of the Tsarist, Provisional Government, and Soviet periods. There is also extensive coverage of World War II. Ceremonial events, such as May Day and October Revolution anniversaries and funerals of prominent figures, including Tolstoy and Lenin, are well represented. Coverage extends into the 1970's. Some Soviet feature films, such as "Kombrig Ivanov," made in 1923, are also included. According to Dr. Raymond Fielding, a leading film expert, the Axelbank Collection is "undoubtedly the largest and most valuable film collection devoted to the subject of revolutionary and pre-revolutionary Russia in the Western hemisphere, and probably in the Western world."
How to Use the Guide
The original film held by the Hoover Institution Archives is on 35 mm positive stock; Axelbank had the earlier reels converted from nitrate to acetate-base (safety) stock.
To facilitate description of the contents of the film, each reel is divided into segments, and the segments into feet.
The type of film is described according to the following alphabetic code.
Actuality: incorporating two classes of "real life" film
"Live" film of an event either totally unplanned or at least planned primarily for purposes other than film-making
Factual material - demonstrations of equipment, interviews, speeches, comment - specially filmed for inclusion in instructional films, news reports, etc.
Dramatisation: film retaining an essentially documentary approach to its subject without meeting either of the "Actuality" definitions
Fiction
Illustrative material: maps, graphs, diagrams, reproductions of photographs and illustrations from books
(Adapted from Imperial War Museum. Department of Information Retrieval. Film Cataloguing Handbook, by Roger B. N. Smither with David J. Penn. London, 1976)
The film is black and white unless the word "color" appears at the bottom of the segment description in the Guide.
Container List
- Summary of Russian history (0-150), 5th century-1868; Segment 1 (Reel 1)
  Beginning of segment:
  0 (1/006)
  Riurik; Sineus; Truvor; Peter the Great; Catherine the Great; Marx, Karl
  D. Text in English interspersed with maps, reproductions of portraits, and illustrations from books
  Sound: 148-150
  English
- Lenin's life from 1869-early 1890's--views of Simbirsk; interior of Ul'ianov house; Ul'ianov family photo including Lenin as a boy; Volga River; Schl[UNK]usselburg Prison; document relating to Alexander Ul'ianov's execution; photo of Lenin; Kazan; University of Kazan; photo of Lenin; Kazan Prison; Lenin's prison cell; photo of Lenin; Lenin's prison dossier; photo of Lenin (150-339) views of pre-revolutionary peasant life--peasant thatched roof wood houses; peasant plowing; peasants threshing; peasant families in boat on river; boatmen; workers in small factory (339-373), 1869-ca. 1914; Segment2; 01:10:09 (Reel 1)
  150 (1/087)
  Lenin, Vladimir Il'ich; Ul'ianova, Mariia Il'inichna; Ul'ianov family
  Plowing; Peasantry; Boatmen; Threshing; Shlissel'burgskaia tiur'ma Ul'yanovsk; Kazan; Volga River
  A. Film of Simbirsk; Ul'ianov house (restored as a museum); Kazan; Volga River; peasants. D. Photos of people and documents; illustrations from books
  Sound: 150-163
- Photos of St. Petersburg--buildings, monuments, factory districts; Lenin at 23; house where Lenin carried on revolutionary activities; illus. of Lenin and other revolutionaries; pages from Lenin's works; photo of Lenin and other members of Union of Struggle for the Emancipation of the Working Class, including Martov (on Lenin's left) and Krzhizhanovskii (on his right) (photo taken February 1897); prison watchtower with guard, prison cell; illus. of Lenin in cell writing; demonstration of invisible ink; cell; photo of Lenin (0-90) film of Siberian area where Lenin was exiled; village of Shushinskaia (place of Lenin's 1897 exile); interior of hut (90-120) illus. of Lenin writing; pages from his works; map (120-130) scenes from cities of St. Petersburg (suburb), Pskov, Nizhni Novgorod, Riga, St. Petersburg (130-144) typescript of one of Lenin's works; photo of Lenin; pages of Iskra; illus. of clandestine printing; map; clandestine printing press; pages; illus. of Lenin speaking to 2d Congress of Russian Social Democratic Workers Party; photo of Stalin; photo of Stalin, Lenin, Kalinin; snowy scenes from villages of Kurena and Katurm, Stalin's Siberian exile sites (144-246), early 1890's-1904; Segment 1; 01:10:15:05-01:17:07:11 (Reel 2)
  0 (1/184)
  Lenin, Vladimir Il'ich; Stalin, Iosif; Martov, IUlii Osipovich; Krzhizhanovskii, Gleb Maksimilianovich
  Soiuz bor'by za osvobozhdenie rabochego klassa
  Leningrad; Shushinskaia; Siberia; Kurena; Katurm; Riga; Pskov; Gor'kii (R.S.F.S.R)
  A. Cities and villages. D. Photos of people and documents, illus. from books, maps
  Sound: 228-233 (Russian); 234-246 (English)
- Priest blessing troops; military parade; spectators throwing flowers; soldiers boarding trains, battle scenes; wagons carrying wounded; naval bombardment; moving troop train; wounded being unloaded from train (246-298), 1904; Segment 2; 01:17:07:12 01:18:34: (Reel 2)
  246 (1/272)
  Military ceremonies--Tsarist period; Russo-Japanese War, 1904-1905; Wounded in battle; Orthodox Eastern Church, Russian
  A; B. Battle scenes
  Sound: 246-290
- Bloody Sunday--soldiers and demonstrators clash; Winter Palace Square; bridge; reproduction of a painting of massacred civilians (298-318) prisoners walking in chains (318-323) burial of Grand Duke Sergei Aleksandrovich, who had been assassinated by SR terrorist (323-340) workers leaving a factory; crowds of workers; orators (340-348) Scenes from the Sergei Eisenstein film Battleship Potemkin (1925): Potemkin mutiny (348-356) crowds of people running down long flights of stairs, being fired upon by soldiers (356-367), 1905; Segment 3; 01:18:35:10 01:20:30:00 (Reel 2)
  298 (1/289)
  Sergei Aleksandrovich, Grand Duke
  Funeral service--Sergei Aleksandrovich, Grand Duke; Revolution of 1905; Prisoners
  Leningrad
  A. Burial of Grand Duke. B. 1905 Revolution scenes
  Sound: 300-312, 319-322
- Cavalry breaks up advancing crowd; rebels battle tsar's forces at the barricades; sequence ends with a proclamation of the tsar with a bloody hand superimposed (0-56) illus. from book of Lenin addressing an illegal meeting in St. Petersburg in 1906 (56-78) film of prison and prison yard; prisoners in cells, walking in chains (78-92) illus. from book of Lenin fleeing into exile across ice of Gulf of Finland (92-100), 1905-1906; Segment 1 (Reel 3)
  0 (1/313)
  Lenin, Vladimir Il'ich
  Prisoners; Prisoners, Political; Revolution of 1905
  A. Prison scenes. B. 1905 Revolution scenes. D. Illus. from books
- Outdoor Te Deum for Imperial Guards regiment; Grand Duke Cyril present (1907)(100-190) Tsar playing tennis (1908)(190-196), 1907, 1908; Segment 2; 01:26:07 (Reel 3)
  100 (1/343)
  Nicholas II, Emperor; Kirill Vladimirovich, Grand Duke; Romanov,
  House of--Recreation
  Orthodox Eastern Church, Russian; Tennis
  A
- Paris and Lenin's Paris home; workers' suburbs (197-235) drawing of Lenin at the time, reprod. of book illus.; photo of Lenin; Lenin's party school at Longjumeau, suburb of Paris (235-240) Tsar and his honor guard (240-243), 1908 (Tsar); Segment 3; 01:26:08:19 01:27:26 (Reel 3)
  196 (1/371)
  Lenin, Vladimir Il'ich; Nicholas II, Emperor
  Rossiiskaia sotsial-demokraticheskaia rabochaia partiia
  France; Paris; Longjumeau, France
  A; D. Illus. from books
- Tolstoi sitting, writing in notebook (243-254) view of Yasnaya Polyana--estate buildings, gates, countryside (254-278) Tolstoi's family (278-289) Tolstoi walking with his wife (289-299) Tolstoi walking (299-306) Tolstoi sawing wood (306-314) Tolstoi walking with dog (314-317) surrounding countryside, birch trees, countryside (317-362), 1909; Segment 4; 01:27:28 01:30:46 (Reel 3)
  243 (1/384)
  Tolstoi, Lev Nikolaevich; Tolstaia, Sofiia Andreevna (Bers)
  Tolstoi family
  Yasnaya Polyana
- Countryside surrounding Yasnaya Polyana; Tolstoi and peasants (0-19) Tolstoi riding horseback (19-42) trip to Moscow by train, September 1909;departure from station with wife; arrival in Moscow; departure; crowd at train station (42-123) stationmaster's house at Astapovo where Tolstoi died; Tolstoi on deathbed (123-139) Tolstoi's funeral procession including Yasnaya Polyana peasants with banner; grave (140-191), 1909-1910; Segment 1; 01:30:57 (Reel 4)
  0 (1/419)
  Funeral service--Tolstoi, Lev Nikolaevich
  Yasnaya Polyana; Astapovo; Moscow
- Tsarist emblems, double-headed eagle; Fortress of Peter and Paul; lifeguards regiment marching; procession of priests; Shrine of the Iberian Virgin, woman kneeling; street scene (191-216) peasant women shoveling, dumping buckets of grain into cart; peasants threshing; thatched roofed huts (repeat of film on reel 1, segment 2); migrating peasants at train station; barge haulers; dockworkers loading grain; miners (217-285) political prisoners, Peter-Paul Fortress; prisoners in railroad cars on way to exile in Siberia (286-339) Tsar and family; Tsarevich and cousin; Tsarevich on pony (340-365), 1911 (Romanovs); Segment 2 (Reel 4)
  191 (1/468)
  Nicholas II, Emperor; Alexandra, Empress Consort of Nicholas II, Emperor; Ol'ga Nikolaevna, Grand Duchess; Tat'iana Nikolaevna, Grand Duchess; Mariia Nikolaevna, Grand Duchess; Anastasiia
  Nikolaevna, Grand Duchess; Aleksei Nikolaevich, Tsarevich Peasantry; Prisoners, Political; Workers; Chasovnia Iverskoi ikony Bozhiei Materi
  Leningrad; Moscow
  A; B. Barge haulers sequence?
  Sound: 191-344
  English; Russian with English voiceover translation
- Ural'sk (fishing village) (0-18) Kursk--fire drill by Kursk fire company; street scenes (18-75) Moscow--Kremlin; Shrine of the Iberian Virgin; Red Square, 1911; Bolshoi Theater; Kremlin; bird market; samovar market (76-205) St. Petersburg--Nevskii Prospekt (206-230) Moscow--Ivan Bell Tower (231-235) Tsar's hunting lodge; hunting dogs (236-250) a northern outpost--windmill (250-255), 1907-1913; Segment 1 (Reel 5)
  0 (1/511)
  Romanov, House of--Recreation
  Chasovnia Iverskoi ikony Bozhiei Materi; Fire departments; Markets; Fishing villages; Hunting lodges; Hunting dogs; Windmills Ural'sk; Kursk; Moscow; Leningrad
  Sound: 236-250
- St. Petersburg--procession with Tsar on horseback and Empress in carriage (255-276) Kremlin--Tsar and family, Grand Duke Michael and his wife at a religious ceremony (276-300) Tsar and family leaving another religious ceremony (Tsarevich has swollen cheek) (300-306) Moscow--section titled: Narodnaia gulian'ia na Devich'em pole (people strolling in Devichoe field, a park) (306-318) building a log house (318-333) Tuapse on the Black Sea--outdoor cafe (333-345) Matsesta Valley (345-354) Lake Baikal--film shot from moving train on Trans-Siberian Railroad (354-362), 1907-1913; Segment 2 (Reel 5)
  255 (1/569)
  Nicholas II, Emperor; Alexandra, Empress Consort of Nicholas II, Emperor; Aleksei Nikolaevich, Tsarevich; Ol'ga Nikolaevna, Grand Duchess; Tat'iana Nikolaevna, Grand Duchess; Mariia Nikolaevna, Grand Duchess; Anastasiia Nikolaevna, Grand Duchess; Mikhail Aleksandrovich, Grand Duke; Natal'ia, Grand Duchess
  Orthodox Eastern Church, Russian; Log houses; Cafes; Carpenters; Processions--Tsarist period
  Leningrad; Moscow; Tuapse; Matsesta Valley; Black Sea Region
  Baikal Lake Region
- Tsar on horseback leading carriage with Empress and Tsarevich; Tsar and Empress on foot among dignitaries (0-7) Title: Reval (Estland)--view from moving train, outskirts of city, wooden buildings (8-23), 1911 (Tsar); c.a. 1911 (Reval); Segment 1 (Reel 6)
  0 (2/006)
  Nicholas II, Emperor; Alexandra, Empress Consort of Nicholas II, Emperor; Aleksei Nikolaevich, Tsarevich Tallinn
  Sound: 0-7
- Title: Straight Through Russia--begins at train station; film shot from moving train; snowy countryside; villages along the tracks (23-138) Moscow--film shot from top of Church of the Redeemer; Kremlin; Moskva River; distillery across the river (138-197) Karelian fishing village--villagers folding the nets; sorting fish; village women self-consciously smiling at camera (197-237) Saratov--street scenes; church with scaffolding; horse-drawn carts; people in overcoats (237-284), c.a. 1911; Segment 2; 07:43:16 (Reel 6)
  23 (2/020)
  Villages; Fishing villages
  Moscow; Karelia; Saratov
- Tsar and Empress walking outdoors among dignitaries, priests; Tsarevich being carried by cossack officer (284-294) Russian gymnasts at 1912 Olympics at Stockholm, Sweden; gymnast on bar; group floor exercises (294-318) Prague scenes; illus. from book of Lenin in Prague; title pages of his What Is To Be Done, One Step Forward, Two Steps Back; mastheads of Pravda showing its frequent title changes (318-386) Tsar outside with camera, taking pictures of his daughters and courtiers; Tsar watching daughters and courtiers play a game--two courtiers and one girl run until one of the courtiers catches the girl; the three then come back and another group of three starts running (386-410), c.a. 1911-1912; Segment 3; 07:43:18 (Reel 6)
  284 (2/146)
  Lenin, Vladimir Il'ich; Nicholas II, Emperor; Alexandra, Empress Consort of Nicholas II, Emperor; Aleksei Nikolaevich, Tsarevich; Ol'ga Nikolaevna, Grand Duchess; Tat'iana Nikolaevna, Grand Duchess; Mariia Nikolaevna, Grand Duchess; Anastasiia Nikolaevna, Grand Duchess; Romanov, House of--Recreation
  Gymnasts; Olympic Games, Stockholm, 1912; Rossiiskaia sotsial-demokraticheskaia rabochaia partiia Czechoslavakia; Prague; Sweden; Stockholm A; D. Illus. from book; reprod. of title pages
  Sound: 294-318
  Music
- Tsar, daughters, courtiers at picnic; playing game in which they are throwing dozens of balls a little larger than softballs at each other (0-65) clowning for camera--courtier dives fully dressed into lake; another paddles out in kayak and purposely capsizes it (65-112) courtiers swimming in the nude (112-158) Tsarevich and courtiers with pony (158-202) playing shuffleboard on the royal yacht (202-261) Tsar's daughters and courtiers rollerskating on the yacht (261-302) scenes of Moscow; scenes of provincial Russia (302-316) estate of the governor of the Kaluga District; governor and wife; peasant district heads (316-351) 1913--St. Petersburg scenes; Tsar's daughters dancing with naval officers aboard a battleship (351-371) Tsar reviewing troops on a railroad platform (373-379), 1912-1914; Segment 1; 02:11:02 (Reel 7)
  0 (2/198)
  Nicholas II, Emperor; Ol'ga Nikolaevna, Grand Duchess; Aleksei Nikolaevich, Tsarevich; Tat'iana Nikolaevna, Grand Duchess; Mariia Nikolaevna, Grand Duchess; Anastasiia Nikolaevna, Grand Duchess; Romanov, House of--Recreation
  Dancing; Swimmers; Roller-skating; Military ceremonies--Tsarist period; Peasantry Leningrad; Kaluga
  Sound: 302-371
- Big Bertha; Krupp Works at Essen; new German destroyer launched at Kiel (0-28), 1913; Segment 1; TAPE 2 has frame line problem USE TAPE # 7 07:04:25:17 07:05:37:21 (Reel 8)
  0 (27/132)
  Krupp'sche Gussstahlfabrik, Essen; Ships--Germany--Launching Germany; Essen, Germany; Kiel, Germany
  Sound: 0-28
- Russian regiment on parade in honor of 300th anniversary of Romanov dynasty (28-37) anniversary celebration at Kremlin; crowds; priests (37-55) Duma in session; illus. of Grigorii Petrovskii, one of the Bolshevik deputies, being ejected from Duma (55-65) groups of Duma deputies, Senators; two men coming out of a door together; Rodzianko, Chairman of the Duma; Purishkevich; Miliukov; group of Duma members (55-89) soldiers on parade at Kremlin; Tsar, on horseback, salutes; priests lead royal procession; Tsar; Empress nods to crowd; Tsarevich; Grand Duchesses; crown jewels; Moscow garrison on parade in Red Square in honor of 300th anniversary of Romanov dynasty; Tsar and Tsarevich followed by Grand Duke Nikolai Nikolaevich; Tsar and family; Tsar, Empress in receiving line; Empress gives gifts to guardsmen (89-173), 1913; Segment 2; 07:05:33: 07:09:18:26 (Reel 8)
  28 (27/144)